<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here begynneth the accedence diligently correcte and poyntyd</title>
            <author>Stanbridge, John, 1463-1510.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1504</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12857</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23153.6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2339</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23282247</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23282247</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26506</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12857)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26506)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1803:41)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here begynneth the accedence diligently correcte and poyntyd</title>
                  <author>Stanbridge, John, 1463-1510.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. Faques,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1504?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publisher and date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Illustrated t.p.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: fragment.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Latin language --  Grammar --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26506:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 34 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:26506:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 34 -->
            <p>¶ Here begynneth the Accedence diligen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tly correcte and poyntyd.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>HOw many partes of reaſon ben there Eyght. whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che eyght? Nowne: pronowne verbe: aduerbe: par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiple: coniunction. <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>poſition. and interiection ¶ How many be declined. &amp; how many be vndeclined. Foure be de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clined.  and foure be vndeclined. whiche foure be declined.
<pb facs="tcp:26506:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 35 -->Nowne / pronowne / verbe. and ꝑticiple. whiche foure ve vndeclined? aduerbe / coniunction / prepoſition / &amp; interie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. ¶ Howe many be declyned with caſe / &amp; howe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny without caſe? Thre be declined with caſe / &amp; one w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out caſe. whiche thre be declined with caſe? nowne / pronowne and participle be declined with caſe / &amp; verbe onely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out caſe ¶ Howe knoweſt a nowne? For all maner thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge / what a man maye ſe / fele / here / or onderſtonde: that be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth the name of a thynge: is a nowne ¶ How many ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of nownes be thre. Two: I nowne ſubſtantyf / and a nowne adiectyf. ¶ How knoweſt a nowne ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tif? for he may ſtande by hym ſelfe without helpe of another wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de: and is declined in latin wich one article / or two at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſte in one caſe / as hic magiſter / hic et hec ſacerdos.</p>
            <p>¶ Howe knoweſt a nowne adiectyf? For he maye not ſtande by hym ſelfe withoute helpe of a nother worde: and is declined in latyn with thre articles / or with thre diuers endynges in one caſe / as noi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>atiuo hic &amp; hec &amp; hoc felix / bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus bona bonum. ¶ Howe many thingis longe to a nowne? Sex. whiche ſex? Qualite / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der / nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber / fygure &amp; caſe. what is qualite in a nowne? a ꝓperte by the whiche a nowne accordeth oonly to one thynge: as Adam / or to many other as men. ¶ Howe knoweſt a qualite in a nowne For it is a ꝓperte: by the whiche one thynge is lykened to a nother: as fayre / ; whyte / blacke.</p>
            <p>¶ Howe many degrees of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paryſons by there? ¶ Thre whiche thre? The poſityf / the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paratyf and the ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyf. ¶ Howe knoweſt the poſityf degre? For he is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of all other degres of comparyſon without makynge more or leſſe: as fayre / whyte / blacke. ¶ Howe knoweſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>patatyf degre? For he paſſeth his poſityf with this abuerbe more / &amp; his englyſſhe endeth in r / as more wyſe / </p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26506:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 35 -->Ambo / duo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> mari neutru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faciunt ſimilari.</p>
            <p>¶ Howe knoweſt the thyrde declenſon? For the genityf ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe ſinguler endeth in is / the datyf in I / the accuſatyf in em or in im / the vocatyf ſhall be lyke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nominatyf / the abla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyf in e / or in i / the nominatyf / accuſatyf and the vocatyf plurel endeth in es / the genityf plurell in um / or in ium / the datyf &amp; the ablatyf in bus. ¶ How knoweſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth declenſon? For the genityfe caſe ſinguler / the nominatyf the accuſatyf / and the vocatyf plurel endeth in us: the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyf in ui. the accuſatyf in um. the vocatyf ſhall be lyke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nominatyf. the ablatyf in u. the genityf plurell in um the datyf and the ablatyf in bus. Alſo all theſe nownes: that be conteyned in theſe verſes: haue u before bus in the da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyf and the ablatyf caſe plurel. All other kepe ſtyll i ſhort afore bus.</p>
            <p>Verſus.
<q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>Ante bus u ſeruant ficus: tribus arcus, acuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>.</l>
                  <l>Artus: cum verubus. portus. partuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>.</l>
                  <l>Et ſpecus. et quercus hic hec hoc reperimus.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Howe knoweſt the fyfte declenſon? for the genityf. and the datyf caſe ſinguler endeth in ei. the accuſatyf in em. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vocatyf ſhalbe lyke the nominatyf. the ablatyfe in e / the nominatyf. accuſatyf. and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vocatyf plurell endeth in es the genityf in erum. the datyfe and the ablatyfe in ebus. Alſo all nownes of the fyfte declenſon lacke the genityf the datyfe. and the ablatyf plurell: out take theſe in theſe verſes folowynge.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Deſunt plurali genitiui: ſiue datiui.</l>
               <l>Et ſexti quinte: niſi res ſpecieſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dieſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</l>
               <l>Progenies et maneries: ſic materieſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</l>
               <l>Ac acies. facies predictis addere debes.</l>
               <l>Vt brito teſtatur: ſpes illis aſſociatur.</l>
            </q>
            <p>HOwe knoweſt a ꝓnowne? For he is a parte of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb facs="tcp:26506:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 36 -->declined with caſe: and is <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> for a ꝓpre name: and betokeneth as moche as a proper name of a man: and other whyle receyueth certeyne perſone and nombre.</p>
            <p>¶ How many pronownes be ther<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? Fyftene, whiche .xv. Ego / tu ſui ille ipſe iſte / hic / &amp; is: Meus / tuus / ſuus / no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter / and veſter noſtras / and veſtras. ¶ Howe many be primatiues / &amp; howe many be deriuatiues? Eyght be pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiues / and ſeuen be deriuatiues. Whiche eyght he pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiues? Ego / tu ſui ille / ipſe / iſte / hic / and is. whiche ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen be deriuatiues? Meus / tuus ſuus / noſter and veſter / noſtras and veſtras. ¶ Of theſe ſeuen primatiues ſome be only relatyues / and ſom be only demonſtratyues / and ſome be bothe relatyues / &amp; demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtratyues. Vnde verſꝰ.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> demonſtrant ego / tu / ſimul hic / ſimul iſte.</l>
               <l>Iure relatiui gaudet is / at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſui.</l>
               <l>Monſtrant / vel referunt ille / vel ipſe tibi.</l>
            </q>
            <p>¶ Howe knoweſt a ꝓnowne demonſtratyfe? for by hym is ſome thynge ſhewed. ¶ Howe knoweſt a ꝓnowne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latyfe? For by hym is ſome thynge ſhewed: that is ſayde byfore. ¶ Howe many pronownes haue the vocatyf caſe and howe many lacke? Foure haue / and all other lacke.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Quattuor exceptis pronomina nulla vocabis.</l>
               <l>Tu meus et noſter / noſtraſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hec ſola vocantur.</l>
            </q>
            <p>¶ Howe many thynges longe to a pronowne? Sex. whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſex? Qualite / gender / nomber / figure / perſon &amp; caſe. ¶ Howe many perſones be ther? Thre. whiche thre? The fyrſt / the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / the thirde. ¶ How knoweſt the fyrſt per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſone? For he ſpeketh of hymſelf as For we ¶ Howe kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weſt the ſeconde perſone? for he ſpeketh to a nother: as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>. or ye. ¶ Howe knoweſt the thirde perſon. For he ſpeketh of a nother as he or they. and euery nowne: pronowne: and Particyple is the .iij. perſon out take ego: et nos: tu</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
